<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Roussel.</title>
<link>https://ddrous.github.io/posts.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://ddrous.github.io/posts.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.433</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Jul 2023 23:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Mesh-free simulation in the age of Big Data</title>
  <dc:creator>RD2N </dc:creator>
  <link>https://ddrous.github.io/posts/mesh-free-simulation/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>This is goign to be about why we need mesh-fre simulations:</p>
<ul>
<li>Meshes are heavy [AsiMov costs 3TB]</li>
<li>Complex geometries can easily be point-clouded rather than meshesd</li>
<li>Most data is represented as point clouds in computer graphics</li>
</ul>



 ]]></description>
  <category>simulation</category>
  <guid>https://ddrous.github.io/posts/mesh-free-simulation/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jul 2023 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A parallel theory of the causal mind</title>
  <dc:creator>RD2N </dc:creator>
  <link>https://ddrous.github.io/posts/parallel-mind-theory/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 
<div class="page-columns page-rows-contents page-layout-article"><div class="social-share"><a href="https://twitter.com/share?url=https://ddrous.github.io/posts/parallel-mind-theory/&amp;text=A complete theory about how the mind and body connect" target="_blank" class="twitter"><i class="fab fa-twitter fa-fw fa-lg"></i></a><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/shareArticle?url=https://ddrous.github.io/posts/parallel-mind-theory/&amp;title=A complete theory about how the mind and body connect" target="_blank" class="linkedin"><i class="fa-brands fa-linkedin-in fa-fw fa-lg"></i></a>  <a href="mailto:?subject=A complete theory about how the mind and body connect&amp;body=Check out this link:https://ddrous.github.io/posts/parallel-mind-theory/" target="_blank" class="email"><i class="fa-solid fa-envelope fa-fw fa-lg"></i></a><a href="https://www.facebook.com/sharer.php?u=https://ddrous.github.io/posts/parallel-mind-theory/" target="_blank" class="facebook"><i class="fab fa-facebook-f fa-fw fa-lg"></i></a><a href="https://reddit.com/submit?url=https://ddrous.github.io/posts/parallel-mind-theory/&amp;title=A complete theory about how the mind and body connect" target="_blank" class="reddit">   <i class="fa-brands fa-reddit-alien fa-fw fa-lg"></i></a><a href="https://www.stumbleupon.com/submit?url=https://ddrous.github.io/posts/parallel-mind-theory/&amp;title=A complete theory about how the mind and body connect" target="_blank" class="stumbleupon"><i class="fa-brands fa-stumbleupon fa-fw fa-lg"></i></a><a href="https://www.tumblr.com/share/link?url=https://ddrous.github.io/posts/parallel-mind-theory/&amp;name=A complete theory about how the mind and body connect" target="_blank" class="tumblr"><i class="fa-brands fa-tumblr fa-fw fa-lg"></i></a><a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="var mastodon_instance=prompt('Mastodon Instance / Server Name?'); if(typeof mastodon_instance==='string' &amp;&amp; mastodon_instance.length){this.href='https://'+mastodon_instance+'/share?text=A complete theory about how the mind and body connect https://ddrous.github.io/posts/parallel-mind-theory/'}else{return false;}" target="_blank" class="mastodon"><i class="fa-brands fa-mastodon fa-fw fa-lg"></i></a></div></div>




<blockquote cite="https://youtu.be/zi7Va_4ekko" class="blockquote"> How do we fit our conception of ourselves (the human reality) with what the world is at its most fundamental level: physical particles and fields of forces ? </blockquote>I’ve always been fascinated by the theory of the mind and how to fully replicate it. Lately, I’ve been finding the philosophical nature of the question more and more fascinating. This article is based on ideas I collected from John Searle’s course <a href="https://youtu.be/zi7Va_4ekko"><em>Philosophy of Mind</em></a>, and Malcolm Gladwell’s best-selling book <a href="https://www.audible.co.uk/pd/Blink-Audiobook/B004F2Z324"><em>Blink</em></a>. Hoping not to get into too much detail, I’ll talk about two technologies I believe are key to deciphering how the human mind works: Neural Ordinary Differential Equations, and Time-Parallel Computing.<p></p>
<section id="the-mind-body-problem" class="level2" data-number="1">
<h2 data-number="1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-mind-body-problem"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> The Mind-Body problem</h2>
<p>The mystery of consciousness is one of the most challenging questions of our time. The Cartesian view postulates that there exists two realms: a real of <strong>Mind</strong> (whose essence is the “thinking”), and a real of <strong>Body</strong> (or the physical)<sup>1</sup>. The mind is indivisible, undoubtable (hence the famous phrase “<em>I think, therefore I am.</em>”), and it commands the body. Of course, this is a gross oversimplification of René Descartes’s legacy, whose ideas we carry to this day.</p>
<p>This formulation dating back to the 17th century is convenient for its time, as it leaves the realm of the Body to science, and the realm of the Mind to religion. Perfect if you’re a scientist trying to conduct thought-provoking research under the Inquisition. Descartes’s theory is appealing, but it leaves us with one big problem. How does the mind influence the brain ? How are the two realms connected ? Descartes’s answer to this puzzle was unconvincing.</p>
<p>Over the centuries, several schools of thought have emerged, only considering one of the two realms. The main groups being <strong>idealism</strong> and <strong>behaviourism</strong>, beautifully explained by John Searle in his course <a href="https://youtu.be/zi7Va_4ekko">Philosophy of Mind</a>. It would appear that the advent of computers and the emergence of the cross-disciplinary field of <strong>cognitive science</strong> is the key to this puzzle.</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/zi7Va_4ekko" title="Philosophy of Mind - Lecture 1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</section>
<section id="the-causal-brain" class="level2" data-number="2">
<h2 data-number="2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-causal-brain"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> The causal brain</h2>
<p>Computers function by means of algorithms: carefully established instructions relating an input to an output. If one were to think of the brain (and <strong>daringly</strong> the mind too) as a computer, then the causal relation between the brain and the mind would have to be at the heart of such formalism. That is the essence of cognitive science.</p>
<p>When you feel hunger or joy, there’s no doubt that these are neurobiological processes in your brain firing. This suggests that the mind reacts to the behaviour of the world, it is caused by brain processes. On the other hand, when you go from being unhappy to being ecstatic, we can clearly see a change in the physical disposition of your brain. In other words, your mind is a state of your brain, a feature.</p>
<p>As explained by Searle, the brain <strong>causes</strong> the mind, and the mind is a <strong>feature</strong> of the brain. This would appear paradoxical, but no, it isn’t. It makes sense if we think of the mind as made up of the higher-level processes compared to what we measure in the brain.</p>
<p><strong>How do higher-level features emerge from individual characteristics</strong>? This is the research question we’ve been after. We’ve turned an abstract philosophical question into a very materialistic one. A scientific problem that includes the mind (unlike Descartes’s original formulation). Examples of mind-blowing behaviour emerging from simplistic elementary processes are widespread in nature. My favourite example is the swirl of Starling birds.</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/V4f_1_r80RY" title="Flight of the Starlings" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>This idea isn’t particularly groundbreaking. I’ve recently head on the <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/tag/the-joy-of-why/">Joy of Why</a> podcast about Professor Anil Seth and his pursuit of similar ideas at the University of Sussex.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>As an applied mathematician, the propagation of brain signals and the causality principle between low- and high-level features remind me of two specific tools: <strong>differential equations</strong> and <strong>neural networks</strong>. Therefore, I liken the causality and evolutionary nature of brain processes to ordinary differential equations (ODE): it describes the individual dynamics. I then ascribe the compositionality of such simple behaviour to form larger feature to Deep Neural Networks.</p>
<p>As it turns out, those two concepts have been merged in what is now known as <a href="https://proceedings.neurips.cc/paper_files/paper/2018/hash/69386f6bb1dfed68692a24c8686939b9-Abstract.html">Neural ODEs</a>, typically formulated as follows: <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cbegin%7Balign%7D%0A%5Cfrac%7B%5Ctext%7Bd%7D%20y%7D%7B%5Ctext%7Bd%7D%20t%7D(t)%20&amp;=%20f_%7B%5Ctheta%7D(y,t),%20%5Cqquad%20t%20%5Cin%20%5Dt_0,%20t_f%20%5B%20%5C%5C%0Ay(t_0)%20&amp;=%20y_0,%20%5C%5C%0Az(t)%20&amp;=%20g_%7B%5Ctheta'%7D(%5Ctheta,%20y,%20y_0,%20t,%20t_0,%20t_f),%0A%5Cend%7Balign%7D"> where <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y"> represents the physical state in which the brain is in. The transformative function <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?f_%7B%5Ctheta%7D"> – where the learnable parameters <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctheta"> indicate a Deep Neural Network – dictates how a physical signal is processed inside the brain. The mysterious <strong>readout</strong> function <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?g_%7B%5Ctheta'%7D"> tells us how a brain signal <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_0%5Cin%20%5Cmathbb%7BR%7D%5Eb"> turns into a global mind feature <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?z%20%5Cin%20%5Cmathbb%7BR%7D%5Em"> (with <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?m%5Cgg%20b">, potentially lots more parameters (neurons) involved in forming a mind than to process an elementary signal).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://ddrous.github.io/posts/parallel-mind-theory/MindBodyProblem.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure 1: Illustration of the computational theory of the mind</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>That’s not all. Typical neural networks today can grow to extremely large size: billions of parameters in the weights <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctheta">. What if this neural network doesn’t have a fixed structure? What if the neurons could dynamically adapt to the task at hand? This is the rapidly growing notions of <a href="https://ojs.aaai.org/index.php/AAAI/article/view/16936">Liquid Neural Networks</a> inspired by the efficiency of the worm’s brain, made up of merely 300 neurons.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>The Neural ODE paradigm has found breathtaking success, particularly against <a href="https://openaccess.thecvf.com/content_cvpr_2016/html/He_Deep_Residual_Learning_CVPR_2016_paper.html">ResNets</a>. The Liquid Neural Network on the other hand has shown jaw-dropping performance in autonomous driving. I believe those two could be combined within the <strong>Liquid Neural ODE</strong>, thus unlocking the secrets of consciousness.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-parallel-theory" class="level2" data-number="3">
<h2 data-number="3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-parallel-theory"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> The parallel theory</h2>
<p>As a full-time daydreamer, I also believe any theory of the mind must account for the subconscious. Although not necessarily as envisioned by Sigmund Freud, since I don’t believe those deeply abstract ideas are indispensable to replicating the human mind.</p>
<p>This is why I think there’s a second computer at work in the back of our minds, even when we are awake. The same computer that quickly processes information and lets a car driver avoid pedestrians in an emergency situation. The kind of computer that shows us how we’re all carrying <a href="https://implicit.harvard.edu/implicit/takeatest.html">implicit biases</a>. The same one we make use of on first impressions. The computer in the background that professionals use to identify talent without even knowing things are happening, subconsciously.</p>
<p>If those ideas sound familiar, that’s because they’re collected from Malcolm Gladwell’s bestselling book <a href="https://www.audible.co.uk/pd/Blink-Audiobook/B004F2Z324">Blink</a>. He repeatedly uses the terminology <em>thin slicing</em>. He describes a computer that, given sufficient time and experience in a domain, discards all useless information to make the quickest decisions for our assumed benefit. The moral of the book is, listen to your inner voice, and know when to ignore it.</p>
<p>So, how can this idea complement the Neural ODE (which represents our foreground mind in this analogy)? Well, we parallelise it. The function <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?f"> above, given a smaller input vector <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y"> and smaller weights <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctheta">, should return faster results at competitive accuracy. What I’m describing is combined data- and time-parallelisation (achieved by skipping certain synaptic connections). We train the Neural ODE on a <strong>fine</strong> data-time domain, and we make sure its inference on a <strong>coarser</strong> data-time domain is just as accurate.</p>
<p>Several works have investigated parallel ideas on Neural ODEs, namely <a href="https://epubs.siam.org/doi/abs/10.1137/19M1247620">Gunther’s</a> and <a href="https://proceedings.neurips.cc/paper/2021/hash/89b9c689a57b82e59074c6ba09aa394d-Abstract.html">Massaroli’s</a>. However, they only considered time (or layer) parallelism. Moreover, they focus on the training, rather than inference. Combining data and time for quick inference is a dream I hope to achieve before then end of my PhD (2025).</p>
</section>
<section id="closing-toughts" class="level2" data-number="4">
<h2 data-number="4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="closing-toughts"><span class="header-section-number">4</span> Closing toughts</h2>
<p>I’m currently investigating the feasibility of a data-time parallel Neural ODE. How would we test such an idea on the brain? I have no clue yet. What I know is that I can start with my brain, as in the famous <a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/chinese-room/">Chinese Room</a> argument.</p>
<p>If your mind finds itself drawn to these ideas, then maybe they’re valid (as Searle says, “<em>always test the theory on yourself first</em>”). In that case, <a href="https://ddrous.github.io/about.html#contact-me">send me a message</a>. If you’ve heard these same ideas somewhere else and think I’m wasting my time or that there’s room for collaboration, then please do reach out. If this sounds like complete nonsense to you, then maybe it is. But it shouldn’t stop us from pursuing the truth, right ?</p>
<p>Please comment below for any insights you might have. And as always, thanks for reading !</p>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>This is the best I can do the define what the mind is, as opposed to what the body is.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Cognitive Science</category>
  <category>Parallel Computing</category>
  <category>Differential Equations</category>
  <guid>https://ddrous.github.io/posts/parallel-mind-theory/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jul 2023 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Welcome to our brand new website</title>
  <dc:creator>RD2N </dc:creator>
  <link>https://ddrous.github.io/posts/welcome/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>This is my very first post in this blog. Welcome!</p>
<p><img src="https://ddrous.github.io/assets/images/fluidflow.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>I’ve never really owned a blog. Even though it’s been on my mind for more than 2 years now.</p>
<p>Now that I’ve got a band new portfolio website, I feel like I’m never going to get a better opportunity than this to flesh out some of my ideas.</p>
<p>The previous iterations of my personal websites are not accessible anymore. But snapshoots can be found below.</p>
<ul>
<li>Photo of Version 1: <a href="https://desmond-rn.github.io">FOS version 1</a></li>
<li>Photo of Version 2: <a href="https://rousseldesnzoyem.com">FOS version 2</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Nothing was wrong with either of those versions. My only concern was that I couldn’t write code like in iPython notebooks. That feature is something I rely on a lot for my Data Science tutorials.</p>
<p>This version of the FOS (version 3) website is built on Quarto which fully support in-line code cells in Python and Julia, my main scripting languages. It offered template more gorgeos than anything that I could’ve found anywhere else.</p>
<p>It is a bit slower though.</p>
<p>Now that you know my reasons for making these changes, you can tell me what you think. <strong>Which version of FOS looks the best accoring to you</strong> ?</p>
<p>POOL</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <guid>https://ddrous.github.io/posts/welcome/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2023 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
